<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>José Antonio Martínez-Rodríguez</title>
<link>https://jamrbaserunningscience.netlify.app/articles.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://jamrbaserunningscience.netlify.app/articles.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.3.353</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 04:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Between-Session Reliability of GPS Technology for Quantifying Linear and Curvilinear Base-Running Performance</title>
  <link>https://jamrbaserunningscience.netlify.app/articles/GPS_reliability.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<section id="context" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="context">Context</h2>
<p>The first peer-reviewed scientific publication emerging from the Carlos Beltran Baseball Academy—an institution inspired by the standards of a Hall of Famer—marks a decisive step forward in Sport Science by placing Base Running Science at the forefront of evidence-based baseball performance.</p>
<p>This peer-reviewed investigation, published in Applied Sciences (2026), evaluated the between-session reliability of 10 Hz GPS technology for quantifying linear (home-to-first) and curvilinear (home-to-second) base-running performance over 54.7 m in trained high school baseball athletes</p>
<p>The study applied a repeated-measures design across three sessions and examined systematic change, absolute reliability (coefficient of variation, CV), relative reliability (intraclass correlation coefficient, ICC), and practical sensitivity via smallest worthwhile change (SWC).</p>
<p>Key findings of direct relevance to baseball performance departments include:</p>
<p>1, <strong>No statistically significant systematic bias</strong> across sessions for linear or curvilinear metrics.</p>
<ol start="2" type="1">
<li><p><strong>High absolute reliability</strong>, with all CVs &lt;10% and 93% &lt;5%, meeting accepted sport science thresholds for monitoring.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Strong relative reliability</strong> for most time- and speed-based metrics (ICCs frequently &gt;0.75, many &gt;0.90).</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Practically sensitive metrics</strong> (TE ≤ SWC) included:</p></li>
</ol>
<ol type="a">
<li><p>Linear sprint: time to 41.1 m and 54.7 m; velocity at 27.4 m and 41.1 m.</p></li>
<li><p>Curvilinear sprint: speed at 41.1 m; peak speed before first base; peak speed before second base and after first base.</p></li>
</ol>
<p>Importantly, the study advanced beyond traditional timing gates by quantifying velocity-time-distance signatures across true game-specific curvilinear paths (home-to-second), including acceleration, modulation entering first base, and re-acceleration phases. For MLB organizations and performance shareholders, this provides validated, baseball-specific monitoring variables capable of informing return-to-play decisions, longitudinal talent tracking, workload management, and individualized base-running prescriptions.</p>
<p>Objectively, this article represents a structural advancement in base-running research for three reasons:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p><strong>First Reliability Framework for True Baseball Curvilinear Running</strong>: Prior GPS reliability work largely examined soccer or track-based semi-circular protocols. This study uniquely validated GPS metrics using the authentic home-to-second base trajectory, directly reflecting in-game mechanics</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Integration of Reliability with Practical Sensitivity (SWC vs.&nbsp;TE)</strong>: By formally comparing typical error against smallest worthwhile change, the paper moves the field from descriptive measurement toward decision-making science—critical for MLB high-performance departments.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Establishment of Monitoring Benchmarks</strong>: The identification of specific robust metrics (e.g., speed at 41.1 m in both linear and curvilinear contexts) provides the first evidence-based recommendation set tailored specifically to baseball base running.</p></li>
</ol>
<p>Within the broader sport science ecosystem, base running has historically been under-quantified relative to pitching biomechanics and hitting analytics. This publication elevates base running from observational coaching practice to a quantifiable performance domain with validated measurement parameters. As a result, it positions Base Running Science as a legitimate sub-discipline within applied baseball performance research.</p>
<p>For the Carlos Beltran Baseball Academy, this work does more than contribute data—it establishes institutional credibility in peer-reviewed sport science, signaling a transition from development academy to research-driven performance leader.</p>
<hr>
<p><img src="https://jamrbaserunningscience.netlify.app/articles/GPS_reliability.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><strong>Where it’s published:</strong></p>
<p><a href="https://www.mdpi.com/2076-3417/16/5/2224" target="_blank">Read the full article</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>velocity-time-distance measures; high school; baseball</category>
  <guid>https://jamrbaserunningscience.netlify.app/articles/GPS_reliability.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://jamrbaserunningscience.netlify.app/articles/GPS_reliability.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="176" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The need for speed: Linear and curvilinear characteristics in Major League Baseball players</title>
  <link>https://jamrbaserunningscience.netlify.app/articles/need_for_speed.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<section id="context" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="context">Context</h2>
<p>This article is important because it provides contemporary, game-derived sprint performance data from 475 Major League Baseball (MLB) players using high-resolution StatCast-Hawk-Eye tracking technology. Unlike earlier research that relied on hand timing or laboratory sprint tests, this study analyzes actual in-game performance metrics, making the findings highly ecologically valid. By examining linear and curvilinear sprint characteristics within real competition, the article bridges the gap between traditional sprint testing and baseball-specific performance demands. This represents a significant advancement in understanding how speed manifests in elite baseball contexts rather than in generalized track-based assessments.</p>
<p>Additionally, the study challenges the long-standing assumption that linear sprint speed alone determines base running success. It demonstrates that while early acceleration strongly predicts stolen base performance, it does not adequately explain performance in running two bases, which requires curvilinear sprint ability. This distinction is critical because it reveals that base running performance is biomechanically multidimensional. By differentiating linear and curvilinear sprint characteristics, the article reframes base running as a specific performance domain that requires targeted assessment and training strategies.</p>
</section>
<section id="key-claims" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="key-claims">Key claims</h2>
<p>One of the central claims of the article is that early linear acceleration, particularly within the first 13.7 meters (approximately 15 yards), is a primary determinant of successful stolen base performance. Players with higher acceleration capabilities and faster home-to-first times were more likely to succeed in stolen base attempts. This finding emphasizes the importance of short-distance acceleration rather than maximal velocity when evaluating base stealing ability.</p>
<p>A second key claim is that linear sprint speed does not predict performance when running two bases, such as advancing from home to second. Unlike stolen base attempts, which are predominantly linear, advancing two bases requires navigating the curvature of the base path. The study suggests that curvilinear sprinting involves different mechanical and force application demands compared to straight-line sprinting. Therefore, improvements in linear sprint metrics may not necessarily transfer to curvilinear running performance.</p>
<p>Finally, the authors argue that base runners should be assessed and trained for both linear and curvilinear sprint characteristics. Relying exclusively on traditional sprint metrics (e.g., 60-yard dash times) may provide an incomplete evaluation of in-game base running ability. This reinforces the need for more sport-specific performance profiling within professional baseball environments.</p>
</section>
<section id="practical-takeaways" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="practical-takeaways">Practical takeaways</h2>
<p>The findings of this article have direct implications for assessment protocols in baseball performance programs. Practitioners should prioritize early acceleration testing, particularly 0-5 m and 0-15 m splits, when evaluating stolen base potential. Emphasizing acceleration metrics rather than maximal velocity alone provides a more accurate representation of performance during base stealing scenarios.</p>
<p>For players expected to advance multiple bases, curvilinear sprint testing should be incorporated into evaluation batteries. This may include bend sprint assessments, curved sprint drills, and analysis of inside-leg versus outside-leg force production. Training programs should integrate curvilinear sprint mechanics, deceleration control, and re-acceleration capabilities to better reflect game-specific movement demands.</p>
<p>From a performance and injury prevention perspective, recognizing the mechanical differences between linear and curvilinear sprinting allows for more targeted neuromuscular preparation. Curved sprinting alters ground contact times and force distribution patterns, which may influence tissue loading and asymmetry. Therefore, integrating force profiling and sprint analysis may not only enhance performance but also reduce injury risk.</p>
<p>Overall, the article reinforces that base running performance is not a singular speed quality but rather a complex interaction of acceleration, force application, and movement specificity. Programs that differentiate and train these components are more likely to produce meaningful improvements in competitive outcomes. image: ../assets/articles/CAT.png</p>
<hr>
<p><img src="https://jamrbaserunningscience.netlify.app/articles/Speed.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/387056050_The_Need_for_Speed_Linear_and_Curvilinear_Characteristics_in_Major_League_Baseball_Players" target="_blank">Read the full article</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Base Running</category>
  <category>Sprinting</category>
  <category>Profiling</category>
  <guid>https://jamrbaserunningscience.netlify.app/articles/need_for_speed.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 30 Nov 2024 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://jamrbaserunningscience.netlify.app/articles/Speed.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="145" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Introduction to an advanced change of direction test in baseball and softball: The curvilinear ability test</title>
  <link>https://jamrbaserunningscience.netlify.app/articles/base_running_science.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p><strong>Where it’s published:</strong></p>
<p><a href="https://journals.lww.com/nsca-scj/abstract/2024/06000/introduction_to_an_advanced_change_of_direction.2.aspx" target="_blank">Read the full article</a></p>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://jamrbaserunningscience.netlify.app/articles/base_running_science.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2024 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://jamrbaserunningscience.netlify.app/assets/articles/CAT.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="140" width="144"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
